A Register of the Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov papers
1884-1973
XX876
Hoover Institution Archives
6 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, military documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian participation in World War I, the Russian Civil War, the Don Cossacks, and Russian émigré affairs.
Krasnov, P. N. (Petr Nikolaevich), 1869-1947.
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Biographical Chronology
1869 September 22 Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1888 Graduated, Pavlovskoe voennoe uchilishche
1903 Author, Po Azii. Putevye ocherki Manchzhurii, Dalniago Vostoka, Kitaia, Iaponii i Indii
1910 Colonel, commanding officer, 1st Siberian Cossack regiment
1913 Commanding officer, 10th Don Cossack regiment
1914 Major General, commanding officer, 1st Don division
1917 Commanding officer, 3rd Cavalry corps
1918 Elected ataman of Don Cossacks Retired
1921 Author, Ot dvuglavogo orla k krasnomu znameni, 1894-1921
1922 Author, Vsevelikoe voisko donskoe
1923 Author, Poniat'-prostit': roman v 4 chastiakh
1927 Author, Dusha armii: ocherki o voennoi psikhologii
1931 Author, Vypash
1937 Author, Nakanunie voiny: iz zhizni pogranichnogo garnizona
1943 Head of Cossack units within the German Army
1945 Turned over by the British Army to Soviet authorities, along with thousands of Cossacks at Lienz, Austria
1947 January 16 Executed, Moscow (?), USSR
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the literary activities of General Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov, Don Cossack Ataman, writer and historian. Most of his writings in emigration focus on the events leading up to the Russian revolution, as well as on the revolution and its aftermath themselves. Krasnov also focused on the history of the Don Cossacks. His writings have been published in translation in English, German and other languages. This collection consists of detailed correspondence mainly related to his writings and personal matters, and also reviews of his published works. The Speeches and Writings file consists mainly of correspondence related to and reviews of his writings.
The Subject File consists of various materials on the Don Cossacks, including minutes of meetings, reports, official documents and publications, dating from 1917 to 1944.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Don Cossack File, Printed Matter, and Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov was born into a Cossack military family: his father was a lieutenant-general, his grandfather, a general. Krasnov graduated from the Pavlovskoe voennoe uchilishche in 1888. He began his literary career early, authoring a log of his travels in the Far East in 1903. In 1910, Krasnov served as colonel and commanding officer of the First Siberian Cossack regiment. By 1914, Krasnov had risen to the rank of major general of the First Don division. Fleeing to the Don region to escape the Russian revolution, Krasnov was elected ataman of the Don Cossacks in 1918, after which he ousted the Soviets from the Don region and headed up the Don Cossack uprising. After suffering the ensuing defeat, Krasnov immigrated to Germany, retired from military life, and devoted himself to his literary career. Petr Nikolaevich Krasnov
During his retirement, General Krasnov published numerous books, many of which were translated into German, English, and other languages. He came out of his military retirement in 1943 to organize and lead Cossack units in the German Army. After Germany’s defeat, General Krasnov was turned over to the Soviet authorities by the British Army. He was hung in Moscow in 1947.
Cossacks.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russia. Armiia--Officers.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.
- Biographical File, 1884-1969 and undated. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles, clippings, family file. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Biographical sketch, "Portrait-Etude P. N. K.. .a,", 1936. (Folder 1: 1)
    Holograph
  - Clippings, 1913-1969 and undated
    - General, 1913-1933 and undated (Folder 1: 2)
    - Fortieth anniversary of Krasnov's literary activities, 1931 and undated. (Folder 1: 3)
      Includes related letter addressed to Konstantin Sergeevich ?
    - Fiftieth anniversary of Krasnov being elevated to rank of officer, 1939 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
    - Hundredth anniversary of Krasnov's birth, 1969 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Family file, 1884
    - Letter, originally accompanied by a print of the tsarevich Nicholas, forwarded as a gift to Nikolai I. Krasnov by Alexander III, 1884 (Folder 1: 6)
- Correspondence, 1919-1944.
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General - Athonite monks, 1930 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Unidentified, 1919-1943, and undated
    - General, 1919-1943 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Anastasiia (?), undated (Folder 1: 9)
    - Anna Nikolaevna (?), 1923-1936 and undated. (Folder 1: 10)
      Includes three newspaper clippings
    - Mila (?), 1943 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Nadezhda (?), 1939 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Petr (?), 1931 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Amfiteatrov, Aleksandr Valentinovich, 1922-1935 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1938 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Annenkov, Boris V., Ataman, 1920 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Antonii (Khrapovitskii), Metropolitan, 1928-1935 and undated (Folder 1: 17)
  - Artifeksov, Leonid Aleksandrovich, undated (Folder 1: 18)
  - Baikov, Nikolai Arkad'evich, 1935-1936 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Berezovskii, Efim Prokop'evich, 1936 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Bratstvo Prepodobnogo Iova Pochaevskogo, 1936 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Buliubash, Evgenii Grigorievich, 1938 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Chebotareva, T., undated. (Folder 1: 23)
    Incomplete letter
  - Chebotari, Mariia, 1940 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Cheslavskii, Vasilii Vladimirovich, undated (Folder 1: 25)
  - Chikhachev, Vladimir, undated (Folder 1: 26)
  - Cochenhausen, von, Conrad, 1939-1943 and undated (Folder 1: 27)
  - Denisov, Sviatoslav Varlaamovich
    - Undated (Folder 1: 28)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 1: 29)
    - 1923-1929 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1930-1938 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 3)
  - D'iakova, E., 1930 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Durnovo, Sofiia Petrovna, undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - Eletskii, Leonid Vasil'evich, Prince, 1925 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Fond imeni velikago kniazia Nikolaia Nikolaevicha, 1929 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Galich, Iurii.
    General note
    See Goncharenko, Iurii, 1938
  - Glaz, Ol'ga, 1922-1938 and undated (Folder 2: 8)
  - Glovatskii, Boris, 1938 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Goncharenko, Iurii, 1932-1936 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Grebenshchikov, Georgii, undated (Folder 2: 11)
  - Herrick, Byron (U.S. Ambassador in Paris), undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - Ioann (?), Archimandrite, 1941 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Ionov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, 1928 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Juvin, Lucien, 1929 and undated (Folder 2: 15)
  - Kasatkin-Rostovskii, Feodor Nikolaevich, 1935-1941 and undated (Folder 2: 16)
  - Khodnev, Dmitrii, 1933-1938 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Kira Kirillovna, Grand Duchess, 1939 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Koverda, Boris, 1937-1938 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Leikhtenbergskii (Leuchtenberg), Georgii Nikolaevich, 1925 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Leikhtenbergskii (Leuchtenberg), Konstantin, 1938 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Militsa Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess, 1924-1943 and undated (Folder 2: 22)
  - Miller, Evgenii K., General, 1930-1931 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Nikolai, Grand Duke of Russia, 1923 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1927 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Omerov, Nika, undated (Folder 2: 26)
  - Orekhov, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1938 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Paleolog, Sergei Nikolaevich, 1924-1929 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Popov, K, 1934 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Popova, N., undated (Folder 2: 30)
  - Postoronkin, Vladimir Nikitich, 1936 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Roman Petrovich, Prince, 1932 (Folder 2: 32)
  - Shcherbachev, A., undated (Folder 2: 33)
  - Shinkarenko, N., 1936-1937 (Folder 2: 34)
  - Shmelev, Ivan Sergeevich, 1936 (Folder 2: 35)
  - Skripkina, Vera, 1937 (Folder 2: 36)
  - Struve, Petr, 1936 (Folder 2: 37)
  - Suvorin, Aleksei Alekseevich, 1921-1922 and undated (Folder 2: 38)
  - Suvorin, Mikhail Alekseevich, 1922-1929 (Folder 2: 39)
  - Svechin, Mikhail Andreevich, 1929 (Folder 2: 40)
  - Turoverov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1938-1941 (Folder 2: 41)
  - Vechernee Vremia, 1919 (Folder 2: 42)
  - Velikoshnaia, T., 1922 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Vera Konstantinovna, Grand Duchess, 1941 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Vinogradov, Vasilii, Archpriest, 1930 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Volkova, Mariia, 1943-1944. (Folder 3: 4)
    Includes photograph
  - Vrangel', Ol'ga, undated (Folder 3: 5)
  - Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich, 1926 and undated (Folder 3: 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1910-1944 and undated.
  Includes articles, contracts, correspondence relating to author's writings, reviews in different languages, arranged according to original order
  - General
    - Open letters, 1921-1934
      - Miscellaneous, 1922-1934 and undated (Folder 3: 7)
      - Pis'ma kazakam, 1921-1927 (Folder 3: 8)
    - "Kto ubival russkikh tsarei,", 1921. (Folder 3: 9)
      Photocopy
    - Lectures, 1936 and undated (Folder 3: 10)
    - "Ob organizatsiiakh,", 1921. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1944
    - General
      - Bookstore "Grad Kitezh,", 1922-1923 and undated (Folder 3: 12)
      - Contracts, documents related to publishing houses and bookstores, 1921-1923 and undated (Folder 3: 13)
      - Controversy regarding Krasnov's article "Tuda i ottuda,", 1928 and undated. (Folder 3: 14)
      - General, 1923-1943 and undated. (Folder 3: 15)
        Includes letters, newspaper clipping
    - Amazonka pustyni, 1932-1939 and undated (Folder 3: 16)
    - Belaia svitka, 1928-1944 and undated (Folder 3: 17)
    - Bozhii tron, 1922 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Domoi, 1936-1943 and undated (Folder 3: 19)
    - Dusha armii, 1928-1941 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Edinaia nedelimaia, 1925-1940 and undated (Folder 3: 21)
    - Ekaterina Velikaia, 1935-1941 and undated (Folder 3: 22)
    - Istoricheskie ocherki Dona, 1944 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Kazaki v Abessinii, 1941 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Largo, 1931-1943 and undated (Folder 3: 25)
    - Lozh', 1939-1942 and undated (Folder 3: 26)
    - Mantyk, 1935-1939 and undated (Folder 3: 27)
    - Na rubezhe Kitaia, 1938-1939 and undated (Folder 3: 28)
    - Nakanune voiny, 1936-1938 (Folder 3: 29)
    - Nenavist', 1934-1935 and undated. (Folder 3: 30)
      Includes correspondence relating to literary award
    - Opavshie list'ia, 1923-1924 (Folder 3: 31)
    - Ot dvuglavogo orla k krasnomu znameni, 1923-1943 and undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Pavlony, 1926-1944 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Podvig, 1932 and undated. (Folder 4: 3)
      Includes letter from Patriarch Varnava (Rusich)
    - Poniat'-Prostit', 1924-1943 and undated (Folder 4: 4)
    - S Ermakom na Sibir', 1930 (Folder 4: 5)
    - S kazakami i kavkazkimi gotsami, 1943 (Folder 4: 6)
    - S nami Bog, 1927 and undated (Folder 4: 7)
    - Tsareubiitsy, 1938-1943 and undated (Folder 4: 8)
    - Tsesarevna, 1933-1934 and undated (Folder 4: 9)
    - Venok na mogilu neizvestnomu soldatu, 1928 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Vse prokhodit, 1926-1931 and undated (Folder 4: 11)
    - Vsevelikoe voisko donskoe, undated (Folder 4: 12)
    - Vypash, 1931-1943 and undated (Folder 4: 13)
    - Za chertopolokhom, 1922-1923 and undated (Folder 4: 14)
  - Reviews, 1910-1944 and undated.
    Includes reviews in Dutch, English, French and German
    - General, 1920-1938 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Amazonka pustyni, 1922-1925 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Arkhiv russkoi revoliutsii, 1921-1922 and undated (Folder 4: 17)
    - Belaia svitka, 1928-1930 and undated (Folder 4: 18)
    - Domoi, 1936-1940 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Dusha armii, 1927-1940 and undated (Folder 4: 20)
    - Edinaia-nedelimaia, 1925-1926 and undated (Folder 4: 21)
    - Ekaterina Velikaia, 1937-1940 and undated (Folder 4: 22)
    - Kartiny bylogo tikhogo dona, 1910 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Largo, 1930 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Lozh', undated (Folder 5: 3)
    - Mantyk, 1929 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Na rubezhe Kitaia, 1939 and undated (Folder 5: 5)
    - Nakanune voiny, 1936-1937 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Nenavist', 1934-1939 and undated (Folder 5: 7)
    - Opavshie list'ia, 1923-1929 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Ot dvuglavogo orla k krasnomu znameni, 1921-1939 and undated (Folder 5: 9)
    - Pavlony, 1944 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Poniat'-prostit', 1924-1929 and undated (Folder 5: 11)
    - S Ermakom na sibir', 1930 and undated (Folder 5: 12)
    - S nami Bog, 1927 (Folder 5: 13)
    - >Step', 1925-1931 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Tsareubiitsy, 1938-1940 and undated (Folder 5: 15)
    - Tsesarevna, 1933 and undated (Folder 5: 16)
    - V Manchzhurskoi glushi, undated (Folder 5: 17)
    - Vse prokhodit, 1925-1927 and undated (Folder 5: 18)
    - Vypash', 1931 and undated (Folder 5: 19)
    - Za chertopolokhom, 1922 (Folder 5: 20)
- Don Cossack File, 1917-1935 and undated.
  Official documents, correspondence, reports and publications of the Don Cossacks, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Don Cossacks in France. (Folder 5: 21)
    Includes materials on the elections of a new Don Cossack ataman, 1935 and undated
  - Kazachii soiuz v Amerike. (Folder 5: 22)
    Includes lists of members, minutes of meetings, statutes, 1934 and undated
    - Obshchestvo revnitelei donskoi istorii i pravdy, 1921 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Official publication of the Vsevelikoe voisko donskoe, title page missing. (Folder 5: 24)
    Includes decisions made by the 4th gathering dedicated to education, 1918. Printed copy
  - Reports No. 361 and 372, signed by Major General Krasnov, 1917 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Sbornik uzakonenii i rasporiazhenii, 1918. (Folder 5: 26)
    Printed copy
  - Shurashov, Ivan, "VI-mu eparkhial'nomu s"ezdu, Donskoi staroobriadcheskoi eparkhii. Doklad,", 1918. (Folder 5: 27)
- Printed Matter, 1929-1931.
  Newspaper and pamphlets, signed and dedicated to P. N. Krasnov
  - Amfiteatrov, Aleksandr, "Literatura v izgnanii," 1929, and "Una letteratura in esilio,", 1930. (Folder 5: 28)
    Printed copies. Dedicated to Petr N. Krasnov and signed by author
  - Sibirskii kazak, 1931. (Folder 5: 29)
    Newspaper signed by A. G. Gryzov, dedicated to Petr N. Krasnov
- Photographs, 1922-1973. (Folder 5: 30)
  Twenty-six prints of Don Cossacks in the diaspora; includes one print of Viacheslav Ivanovich Volkov, signed on reverse by his daughter, and eight prints from a Cossack in Paraguay